<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
  <style type="text/css">
    @media print {
      body { }
      p.img { text-align: center; page-break-inside: avoid }
      img.CC { display: inline }
    }
    @media screen {
      body { max-width: 800px; margin: auto }
      p.img { text-align: center }
      img.CC { display: inline }
    }
    p.date {
      font-size: smaller;
      margin: 0;
    }
    p.versionHistory {
      color: gray
    }
    p.versionHistory a {
      color: gray
    }
    p.ref {
      text-indent: -2em;
      padding-left: 2em;
    }
    p.fig {
      text-align: left;
    }
    p.fig img, img.plot {
      box-shadow: 10px 10px 20px;
      margin-top: 10px;
      margin-bottom: 20px;      
    }
  </style>

</head>
<body>
  <h1>The Path to Path Enlightenment:<br/>
  Stroking and Filling Paths in R Graphics</h1>
  <p>
    <span style="font-style: italic">by Paul Murrell</span>
    <a href="http://orcid.org"><img alt="" src="https://www.stat.auckland.ac.nz/~paul/ORCID/ORCiD.png" style="width: 16px; height: 16px; vertical-align: middle" /></a> <span style="font-family: mono; font-size: small"><a href="http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3224-8858">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3224-8858</a></span>
  </p>
  <p class="date">
    Version 1:  
    <rcode echo="FALSE" results="asis"><![CDATA[
cat(format(Sys.Date(), "%A %d %B %Y"))
    ]]></rcode>
  </p>

  <rcode id="init" echo="FALSE" message="FALSE" results="hide"><![CDATA[
opts_chunk$set(comment=" ", tidy=FALSE, 
               dev="png", ## dev="svg",
               dpi=96)
options(width=100)
## For wonky desktop set up
options(bitmapType="cairo")
  ]]></rcode>
  <rcode echo="FALSE" message="FALSE"><![CDATA[
    library(grid)
  ]]></rcode>

  <hr/>
  <p>
    <a rel="license"
    href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><img class="CC"
    alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
    src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/88x31.png"/></a><br/><span
    xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
    property="dct:title">This document</span>
    by <span xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#"
    property="cc:attributionName">Paul
    Murrell</span> is licensed under a <a rel="license"
    href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative
    Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</a>.
  </p>
  <hr/>
  <p>
    This document describes an expansion of the R graphics engine
    to support stroking and filling paths. 
  </p>
  <p>
    These features are available in the development version of R 
    (to become 4.2.0).
  </p>
  <p>
    R users wanting to try out the new graphics features should start with
    the <a href="#api"/> Section, which provides a quick introduction
    to the new R-level interface.
  </p>
  <p>
    Maintainers of R packages that provide R graphics devices should
    read the <a href="#device"/> Section, which provides a description of the
    required changes to R graphics devices. 
  </p>
  <p>
    These new graphics features have not (yet) been implemented for
    all of the graphics devices provided by the 'grDevices'
    package. Devices that do support the new features are the 
    <code>pdf()</code> graphics device and Cairo graphics devices:
    <code>x11(type="cairo")</code>, <code>cairo_pdf()</code>,
    <code>cairo_ps()</code>, <code>png(type="cairo")</code>,
    <code>jpeg(type="cairo")</code>, <code>tiff(type="cairo")</code>, 
    and <code>svg()</code>.
    The remainder of the graphics
    devices in 'grDevices' will run, but will (silently) not produce
    the correct output. Graphics devices from other R packages should
    be reinstalled and will not produce the correct output until
    (or unless)
    the package maintainer adds support.
  </p>

  <toc/>

  <h2><a name="intro">Introduction</a></h2>

  <p>
    Changes to the graphics engine in R 4.1.0 added support for
    gradient and pattern fills, clipping paths, and masks 
    (<a href="#murrell-definitions-2020"/>).  
    One way to think of those changes is that they
    create an R interface to some of the more advanced graphical features
    of specific R graphics devices;  graphics devices that are based on 
    sophisticated graphics systems, like the <code>pdf()</code> device
    that is based on the Adobe Portable Document Format 
    (<a href="#PDF"/>) and the graphics
    devices based on the Cairo graphics library (<a href="#cairo"/>).
    This document describes another step along that path, by adding 
    an R interface to generate "paths" from a collection of graphical objects.
  </p>
  <p>
    As with the group features that have been recently added to
    R graphics (<a href="#murrell-groups-2021"/>), the main motivation
    behind adding the new path features is to increase the 
    range of graphical output that can be produced entirely with R
    code, so that users do not have to resort to manual tweaks with
    software like Adobe Illustrator.
    As a consequence, the examples in this report involve 
    only basic shapes that demonstrate the fundamental concepts.
    There are no obvious connections to traditional data 
    visualisation, though of course the possibility of 
    future connections arising cannot
    be entirely ruled out.
  </p>
  
  <h3>One shape at a time</h3>
  <p>
    R graphics follows a very simple graphics model:  
    it only draws one shape at a time.  For example, the following
    code draws a circle and then a rectangle. Both shapes have an
    opaque border, but a semitransparent fill, which allows us to 
    see that the rectangle, which is drawn second,
    is drawn on top of the circle.
  </p>

  <rcode><![CDATA[
library(grid)
  ]]></rcode>

  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.circle(.6, .6, r=.2, 
            gp=gpar(col=4, lwd=5, fill=adjustcolor(4, alpha=.5)))
grid.rect(.4, .4, width=.4, height=.4, 
          gp=gpar(col=2, lwd=5, fill=adjustcolor(2, alpha=.5)))
  ]]></rcode>

  <h3>Paths on graphics devices</h3>

  <p>
    R graphics output is sent to a <em>graphics device</em> either to draw
    to the screen, or to record the drawing in a file.  For example,
    the <code>postscript()</code> device records drawing
    in a PostScript file.
  </p>
  <p>
    The simplicity of R graphics means that R graphics devices are only asked to
    draw one shape at a time, e.g., draw a circle <em>then</em> 
    draw a rectangle.
    For example, the PostScript to draw a circle and a rectangle could look like
    the following.  The important part of the code is the clear separation
    into two shapes, each starting with a 
    <code>newpath</code> and ending with a <code>fill</code>
    (to fill the shape).
  </p>

  <rcode echo="FALSE"><![CDATA[
system("convert ps-painters.ps ps-painters.png")
cat(readLines("ps-painters.ps"), sep="\n")
  ]]></rcode>

  <p>
    <img src="ps-painters.png"/>
  </p>

  <p>
    However, many graphics devices support a more sophisticated drawing
    model based on <em>paths</em>.  In this model, a single path can be
    constructed from more than one shape.  For example, the PostScript
    code below draws the same two shapes as before, but draws them
    within a single path (and then fills that single path). In this code,
    we can see only one <code>newpath</code> and only one <code>fill</code>.
  </p>

  <rcode echo="FALSE"><![CDATA[
system("convert ps-path.ps ps-path.png")
cat(readLines("ps-path.ps"), sep="\n")
  ]]></rcode>

  <p>
    <img src="ps-path.png"/>
  </p>

  <p>
    The result in this case is a filled area that is just the union of the
    two individual shapes, but we can get more interesting results by
    controlling how the "inside" of the path is interpreted.  For example,
    the following PostScript code creates exactly the same
    single path from the two shapes, but this time runs <code>eofill</code>
    (rather than <code>fill</code>).  That changes to an "even-odd" fill rule
    (from the default "non-zero winding" rule), so the overlap 
    between the two shapes within the path is now "outside" the overall
    path and we get a shape with a hole in it.
  </p>

  <rcode echo="FALSE"><![CDATA[
system("convert ps-path-hole.ps ps-path-hole.png")
cat(readLines("ps-path-hole.ps"), sep="\n")
  ]]></rcode>

  <p>
    <img src="ps-path-hole.png"/>
  </p>

  <h3>Paths in R</h3>
  <p>
    The changes described in this report allow us to draw these
    more sophisticated paths in R graphics.  As a simple demonstration,
    the following code defines a 'grid' gTree consisting of 
    a circle grob and a rectangle grob.
  </p>
  <rcode><![CDATA[
gt <- gTree(children=gList(circleGrob(.6, .6, r=.2,
                                      gp=gpar(col=4, lwd=5, 
                                              fill=adjustcolor(4, alpha=.5))),
                           rectGrob(.4, .4, width=.4, height=.4,
                                    gp=gpar(col=2, lwd=5, 
                                            fill=adjustcolor(2, alpha=.5)))))
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    If we draw this gTree normally, 
    the circle and the rectangle are drawn
    as separate shapes and we get the rectangle drawn on top 
    of the circle.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.draw(gt)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    With the new changes, we can instead draw the gTree as a single
    path (and fill and stroke the path) with the code shown below.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.fillStroke(gt, 
                gp=gpar(col=2, lwd=5, fill=adjustcolor(2, alpha=.5)),
                rule="evenodd")
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    The result is a single path based on the combination of the circle
    and the rectangle and, because we specified <code>rule="evenodd"</code>,
    that path is filled and stroked using the even-odd rule
    used to determine where to fill.  This means that we get a hole
    in the path where the two shapes overlap.
  </p>

  <h2><a name="api">User API</a></h2>

  <p>
    The new features for stroking and filling paths are only available via
    functions in the 'grid' package (so far).
    The <code>grid.stroke()</code> function strokes a path,
    the <code>grid.fill()</code> function fills a path,
    and the <code>grid.fillStroke()</code> functions fills and 
    strokes a path.
    In all three cases, the path is defined by a 'grid' grob.
    The simplest example is a single shape as in the code below.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.stroke(circleGrob(r=.3))
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    This example behaves just like normal 'grid'
    drawing, but already there are some important differences.
    For example, the following code produces exactly the same
    result even though it is based on a <em>filled</em> circle grob.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.stroke(circleGrob(r=.3, gp=gpar(fill="grey")))
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    This demonstrates an important principle of paths in R:
    <strong>a grob only contributes its outline to a path</strong>.
    The following code demonstrates that this also applies to
    the fill rule for a "path" grob.  
  </p>
  <p>
    First we describe a shape using the <code>pathGrob()</code> 
    function which consists of two rectangles, one nested within the
    other.   This includes a fill rule (<code>winding</code>)
    that means that the
    inner rectangle should be filled.  This shape is drawn on the
    left of the image.  Next, we define a path based on this shape,
    but with a different fill rule (<code>evenodd</code>).  
    When we fill the path, the 
    shape only contributes its outline, its fill rule 
    (<code>winding</code>) is ignored.
    The fill rule for the path (<code>evenodd</code>) is enforced to
    determine the fill region, which means that
    the inner rectangle is NOT filled.  This result is drawn on the right.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="4" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
shape <- pathGrob(c(.2, .2, .8, .8, .4, .4, .6, .6),
                  c(.2, .8, .8, .2, .4, .6, .6, .4),
                  id=rep(1:2, each=4),
                  rule="winding",
                  gp=gpar(fill="grey"))
pushViewport(viewport(x=0, width=.5, just="left"))
grid.draw(shape)
popViewport()
pushViewport(viewport(x=.5, width=.5, just="left"))
grid.fillStroke(shape, rule="evenodd", gp=gpar(fill="grey"))
popViewport()
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    The next example demonstrates one way in which this
    behaviour - shapes only contribute outlines - might be useful.  
    We use a text grob to add
    the outlines of text glyphs to a path and then stroke the path
    to produce outlined text.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.stroke(textGrob("outline", gp=gpar(cex=3)))
  ]]></rcode>  
  <p>
    The next example shows another important point: 
    functions like <code>grid.stroke()</code> have a <code>gp</code>
    argument that controls the graphical parameters that are 
    used to draw the path.  In this case, a circle grob
    with the default line width of 1 is used to define the path.
    The grob only contributes its outline to the path;  its
    line width is ignored.
    The <code>grid.stroke()</code> call specifies a line width of 5,
    so the path is stroked using a thick line.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.stroke(circleGrob(r=.3), gp=gpar(lwd=5))
  ]]></rcode>  
  <p>
    The next example is slightly more complex because it 
    involves a path that is based on more than one shape.
    This code works with a path that is based on two overlapping
    circles.  We use <code>grid.fill()</code> this time to
    fill the path.
    The result is interesting because we have filled the path
    with a semitransparent red (and drawn text underneath 
    to emphasise that we can see through the fill).
    The <code>grid.fill()</code> function fills the "inside"
    of the path, which in this case is the union of the
    two circles.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.text("background")
grid.fill(circleGrob(1:2/3, r=.3), 
          gp=gpar(fill=adjustcolor(2, alpha=.5)))
  ]]></rcode>  
  <p>
    For comparison,
    the following code draws the grob normally (two overlapping circles)
    using a semitransparent red fill, just to emphasise how the
    path-filling behaviour is different.  For a start, drawing
    the grob draws the circle borders (whereas <code>grid.fill()</code>, 
    will only ever fill a path), but more importantly, 
    drawing the grob fills each circle separately, so we get
    an intersection region where the top circle partially overlaps the
    bottom circle.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.text("background")
grid.circle(1:2/3, r=.3, 
            gp=gpar(fill=adjustcolor(2, alpha=.5)))
  ]]></rcode>  
  <p>
    The <code>grid.fill()</code> and <code>grid.fillStroke()</code>
    functions have an additional argument, <code>rule</code>,
    that controls the fill-rule that is used to fill the path.
    The following code again fills a path based on the two overlapping circles, 
    but this time uses the even-odd fill rule.
    This results in a filled path with a hole where the circles 
    overlap.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.text("background")
grid.fill(circleGrob(1:2/3, r=.3), 
          gp=gpar(fill=adjustcolor(2, alpha=.5)), 
          rule="evenodd")
  ]]></rcode>  

  <h2>Clipping paths</h2>
  <p>
    Clipping paths, which were added to the R graphics system
    in R 4.1.0, are also based on 'grid' grobs and they produce
    a single path from multiple shapes just like the paths
    described above.  
  </p>
  <p>
    <strong>The region that output is clipped to, based on a clipping path,
    is the region that would be filled, if that clipping path was
    filled.</strong>
  </p>
  <p>
    Unfortunately, in the original implementation of clipping paths,
    this distinction was not made clear and no facility was provided
    to specify the fill rule for a clipping path.
  </p>
  <p>
    The new function <code>as.path(grob, gp, rule)</code> is designed
    to help fix this problem.
    This function combines a grob with graphical parameter settings
    and a fill rule;  it defines a path, how to fill it, and what
    colours and line types to use when filling or stroking the path.
  </p>
  <p>
    Clipping paths, as already implemented in R 4.1.0 via 
    <code>viewport(clip=grob)</code>, can now also be specified
    via <code>viewport(clip=as.path(grob, gp, rule))</code>.
    This allows the fill rule for a clipping path to be specified 
    by the user.
    The code below demonstrates this by defining two clipping paths,
    both consisting of two overlapping circles, but one using
    the even-odd fill rule and one using the (default) non-zero winding rule.
  </p>
  <rcode><![CDATA[
circles <- circleGrob(1:2/3, r=.3)
clipPath1 <- circles
clipPath2 <- as.path(circles, rule="evenodd")
  ]]></rcode>
  
  <p>
    The following code pushes two viewports, one using the first clipping
    path (on the left) and one using the second clipping path (on the right), 
    and fills a rectangle
    using a checkerboard pattern (code for the pattern not shown).
    We can clearly see that the clipping paths differ based on the
    path fill rule that is used.
  </p>
  <!-- NOTE that this example produces PDF output that displays
       correctly in xpdf AND Adobe Acrobat (but not, e.g., evince) 
  -->
  <rcode echo="FALSE"><![CDATA[
rects <- gTree(children=gList(rectGrob(width=unit(5, "mm"), 
                                       height=unit(5, "mm"),
                                       just=c("left", "bottom"),
                                       gp=gpar(fill="black")),
                              rectGrob(width=unit(5, "mm"), 
                                       height=unit(5, "mm"),
                                       just=c("right", "top"),
                                       gp=gpar(fill="black"))))
pat <- pattern(rects,
               width=unit(1, "cm"), height=unit(1, "cm"),
               extend="repeat")
  ]]></rcode>
  <rcode fig.width="4" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
pushViewport(viewport(x=0, width=.5, just="left", 
                      clip=clipPath1))
grid.rect(gp=gpar(fill=pat))
popViewport()
pushViewport(viewport(x=.5, width=.5, just="left", 
                      clip=clipPath2))
grid.rect(gp=gpar(fill=pat))
popViewport()
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    The functions <code>grid.stroke()</code>, 
    <code>grid.fill()</code>, and <code>grid.fillStroke()</code>
    are all generic so the user can supply a single 
    argument using <code>as.path()</code> rather than specifying
    the grobs, fill rule, and graphical parameters as separate arguments.
    For example, the following two sets of code produce exactly the same
    result.
  </p>
  <rcode eval="FALSE"><![CDATA[
grid.text("background")
grid.fill(circleGrob(1:2/3, r=.3),
          gp=gpar(fill=adjustcolor(2, alpha=.5)),
          rule="evenodd")
  ]]></rcode>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.text("background")
grid.fill(as.path(circleGrob(1:2/3, r=.3),
                  gp=gpar(fill=adjustcolor(2, alpha=.5)),
                  rule="evenodd"))
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    If we want to know what a clipping path is going to look like,
    we can use <code>grid.fill()</code> on the clipping path.  The 
    region that is filled will be the clipped region.
  </p>

  <h2><a name="device">Device API</a></h2>

  <p>
    The good news is that maintainers of R packages that implement
    graphics devices do not need to do anything in response
    to these changes.  Graphics device packages will need to be reinstalled
    for R version 4.2.0, but they do not need to be updated.
    The graphics engine will only make calls to the graphics device
    to stroke or fill paths if the graphics device <code>deviceVersion</code>
    is set to 15 (<code>R_GE_group</code>) or higher.  Of course, if 
    the graphics device has a lower <code>deviceVersion</code>,
    R code that attempts to stroke or fill paths will have no effect.
  </p>

  <h3>A template for no support</h3>
  <p>
    As an example of the (minimal) changes necessary to update a device
    (<strong>without</strong> support for any of the new path features),
    the following diff output
    shows the changes made to the <code>postscript()</code>
    device.
  </p>
  <pre>
@@ -3033,6 +3033,14 @@
+static void     PS_stroke(SEXP path, const pGEcontext gc, pDevDesc dd);
+static void     PS_fill(SEXP path, int rule, const pGEcontext gc, pDevDesc dd);
+static void     PS_fillStroke(SEXP path, int rule, const pGEcontext gc,
+                              pDevDesc dd);

@@ -3495,11 +3503,17 @@
+    dd->stroke          = PS_stroke;
+    dd->fill            = PS_fill;
+    dd->fillStroke      = PS_fillStroke;

-    dd->deviceVersion = R_GE_definitions;
+    dd->deviceVersion = R_GE_group;

@@ -4535,8 +4549,22 @@
+static void PS_stroke(SEXP path, const pGEcontext gc, pDevDesc dd) {}
+
+static void PS_fill(SEXP path, int rule, const pGEcontext gc, pDevDesc dd) {}
+
+static void PS_fillStroke(SEXP path, int rule, const pGEcontext gc,
+                          pDevDesc dd) {}
  </pre>

  <h3>Implementing support for paths</h3>
  <p>
    This section provides information about what to do
    if a graphics device package wishes
    to support the new path features.
  </p>
  <p>
    The <code>dev->deviceVersion</code> must be set to 15
    (<code>R_GE_groups</code>) or higher.
  </p>
  <p>
    A device must implement the new 
    <code>dev-&gt;stroke(path, gc, dd)</code>,
    <code>dev-&gt;fill(path, rule, gc, dd)</code>, and
    <code style="white-space: nowrap">dev-&gt;fillStroke(path, rule, gc, dd)</code> functions.
    The <code>path</code> argument is an R function that the
    device should evaluate to define the path.
    As with clipping paths, masks, and groups,
    this function will generate further calls to the device, which the device
    should "capture" to define the path (rather than drawing immediately).
  </p>
  <p>
    For <code>dev->fill</code> and <code>dev->fillStroke</code>,
    the <code>rule</code> argument is an integer and
    the device should set the fill rule based on this
    (the graphics engine provides <code>R_GE_nonZeroWindingRule</code>
    and <code>R_GE_evenOddRule</code> to switch on).
  </p>
  <p>
    The device should then stroke, fill, or fill and stroke the path
    (ideally, the graphics system being used will have a single
    operator that performs the latter) using the current 
    graphical parameter settings provided in the <code>gc</code> argument.
  </p>
  <p>
    The existing <code>dev-&gt;setClipPath(path, ref, dd)</code> API
    is unchanged;
    the fill rule for the clipping path function is passed in 
    via <code>attr(path, "rule")</code>.
  </p>

  <h3><a name="details">Exemplars</a></h3>
  <p>
    Support for these new features has been implemented for the
    <code>pdf()</code> device and the devices that are based on Cairo
    graphics, so the code for those devices demonstrates some
    possible approaches to implementation.
  </p>
  <p>
    Both Cairo and PDF devices use the "append mode" previously
    introduced for capturing clipping paths 
    (<a href="#murrell-definitions-2020"/>)
    to accumulate a path before stroking or filling it.
  </p>

  <h2><a name="discussion">Discussion</a></h2>

  <h3>Limitations</h3>
  <p>
    The most important limitation to acknowledge is the fact that
    these new features are only currently supported on a subset
    of the core graphics devices:  the <code>pdf()</code> device
    and the devices based on Cairo graphics (e.g.,
    <code>png(type="cairo")</code>,
    <code>cairo_pdf()</code> and <code>svg()</code>).
  </p>
  <p>
    In addition, the <code>pdf()</code> device 
    only allows a single text object within a path
    (no combining text with other drawing in a path).
    Other drawing is just left out of a path that already contains text
    and text is left out of a path
    if other drawing already exists.
    This also applies to clipping paths.
  </p>
  <!--
    "Unlike PostScript, PDF does not allow a single path to mix text
    outlines with lines and curves."
    <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDF#Vector_graphics">Wikipedia</a>.
    -->

  <h3>Listing and editing paths</h3>
  <p>
    As with groups (<a href="#murrell-groups-2021"/>)
    we cannot directly see (<code>grid.ls()</code>) or edit 
    (<code>grid.edit()</code>) the
    grob that defines a path.  However, but with a little extra work,
    it is possible to extract the
    <code>path</code> component of a stroke, fill, or fillStroke
    grob and edit/replace that.
  </p>

  <h3>Related work</h3>
  <p>
    The 'grid' graphics system already had a "path" interface
    with its <code>grid.path()</code> function.
    The difference between that interface and this new one
    is that a <code>grid.path()</code> can only be constructed
    from a set of vertices.
    For example, suppose we want to fill a path from
    two concentric circles, using an even-odd rule (so that the 
    centre is empty).  With the new interface, the
    code is very simple, as shown below.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
grid.fillStroke(circleGrob(r=c(.2, .4)), rule="evenodd", gp=gpar(fill=2))
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    If we want to produce the same result with <code>grid.path()</code>
    we have to construct vertices along the boundaries of the 
    two circles, as shown below.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
t <- seq(0, 2*pi, length.out=50)
circlePts <- function(r) list(x=.5 + r*cos(t), y=.5 + r*sin(t))
c1 <- circlePts(.2)
c2 <- circlePts(.4)
grid.path(c(c1$x, c2$x), c(c1$y, c2$y), id=rep(1:2, each=50),
          rule="evenodd", gp=gpar(fill=2))
  ]]></rcode>  
  <p>
    Another approach to constructing paths from shapes is 
    provided by the 'gridGeometry' (<a href="#pkg:gridGeometry"/>).
    For example, the concentric circle problem can be solved
    using this package
    with the following code.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="2"><![CDATA[
library(gridGeometry)
grid.polyclip(circleGrob(r=.4,), circleGrob(r=.2), "minus",
              gp=gpar(fill=2))
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    One advantage of the 'gridGeometry' approach is that it
    should work for all R graphics devices.
    However, some results, for example
    stroking the outline of text, that are possible with the
    new path features cannot be (easily) achieved with 'gridGeometry'.
  </p>

  <h2><a name="requirements">Technical requirements</a></h2>
  <p>
    The examples and discussion in this report relate to 
    the development version of R (specifically revision 81125),
    which will probably become R version 4.2.0.
  </p>
  <p>
    This report was generated within a Docker container
    (see <a href="#Resources">Resources</a> section below).
  </p>

  <h2><a name="Resources">Resources</a></h2>
  <ul>
    <li>
      The <a href="paths.cml">raw source file</a> for this
      report, a <a href="paths.xml">valid XML</a>
      transformation of the source file, a <a
      href="paths.Rhtml">'knitr' document</a> generated from
      the XML file, 
      two <a href="toc.R">R</a> <a href="bib.R">files</a> and
      the <a href="paths.bib">bibtex file</a>
      that are used to generate the table of contents and reference sections,
      two <a href="common.xsl">XSL</a> <a
      href="knitr.xsl">files</a> and an 
      <a href="knit.R">R file</a> that are used to transform the XML to
      the 'knitr' document, and a <a href="Makefile">Makefile</a> that
      contains code for the other transformations and coordinates
      everything.  
      These materials are also available
      on <a href="https://github.com/pmur002/paths-report/releases/tag/v1">github</a>.
    </li>
    <li>
      This report was generated within a 
      <a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a> container.
      The Docker command to build the report is included in the Makefile above.
      The Docker image for the container is available from
      <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/pmur002/paths-report/">Docker Hub</a>;
      alternatively, the image can be rebuilt from its 
      <a href="Dockerfile">Dockerfile</a>.
    </li>
  </ul>

  <h2>How to cite this report</h2>
  <p>
    Murrell, P. (2021). "Stroking and Filling Paths in R Graphics" 
    Technical Report 2021-03, Department of Statistics, The University of Auckland. 
    Version 1.
    [ <a href="how-to-cite.bib">bib</a> |
      <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.17608/k6.auckland.12649751">DOI</a> | 
      <a href="https://stattech.blogs.auckland.ac.nz/2020/07/14/2020-04-catching-up-with-r-graphics/">http</a> ]
  </p>

  <h2><a name="references">References</a></h2>
  <ul style="list-style-type: none">
    <li>
      <a name="R"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="murrell-definitions-2020"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="PDF"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="cairo"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="murrell-groups-2021"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="pkg:gridGeometry"/>
    </li>
    
  </ul>

  <hr/>
  <p>
    <a rel="license"
    href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><img class="CC"
    alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
    src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/88x31.png"/></a><br/><span
    xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
    property="dct:title">This document</span>
    by <span xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#"
    property="cc:attributionName">Paul
    Murrell</span> is licensed under a <a rel="license"
    href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative
    Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</a>.
  </p>

</body>
</html>
